<indexterm><primary>man page</primary><see>reference guide</see></indexterm>
<indexterm class="startofrange" id="man-ncrack1-indexterm">
  <primary>reference guide (man page)</primary>
</indexterm>
<refentry id='man-ncrack1'>
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>ncrack</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo class="source">Ncrack</refmiscinfo>
    <refmiscinfo class="manual">Ncrack Reference Guide</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv id='man-name'>
    <refname>ncrack</refname>
    <refpurpose>Network authentication cracking tool</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <!-- body begins here -->
  <refsynopsisdiv id="man-synopsis">
    <cmdsynopsis sepchar=" ">
      <command moreinfo="none">ncrack</command>
      <arg choice="opt" rep="norepeat">
        <replaceable>Options</replaceable>
      </arg>
      <arg choice="req" rep="norepeat">
        <replaceable>target specification</replaceable>
      </arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
  <refsect1 id="man-description">
    <title>Description</title>
    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>Ncrack</primary><secondary>
        description of</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <web>
    <note>
    <para>
    This document describes the very latest version of
    Ncrack available from <ulink url="http://ncrack.org/download.html"/> Please
    ensure you are using the latest version before reporting that a
    feature doesn't work as described.
    </para>
    </note>
    </web>
    <para>
      Ncrack is an open source tool for network authentication cracking. 
      It was designed for high-speed parallel cracking using a dynamic engine
      that can adapt to different network situations. Ncrack can also be
      extensively fine-tuned for special cases, though the default parameters
      are generic enough to cover almost every situation. It is built on a
      modular architecture that allows for easy extension to support additional
      protocols. While Ncrack's main purpose is to audit the security of large
      networks for default, weak passwords in a rapid, yet reliable way, it can
      also be used to conduct some fairly sophisticated bruteforcing attacks.
    </para>

    <para>
      The output from Ncrack is a list of found credentials, if any, for each
      of the targets specified. Ncrack can also print an interactive status
      report of progress so far and possibly additional debugging information
      that can help track problems, if the user selected that option.
    </para>

    <para>
      A typical Ncrack scan is shown in
      <xref linkend="man-ex-repscan" xrefstyle="select: label nopage" />. 
      The only Ncrack arguments used in this example are the two target IP
      addresses along with the the corresponding ports for each of them. The
      two example ports 21 and 22 are automatically resolved to the default
      services listening on them: ftp and ssh.
    </para>

    <example id="man-ex-repscan"><title>A representative Ncrack scan</title>
      <indexterm><primary><option>-v</option></primary><secondary>example of
      </secondary></indexterm>
    <screen>

$ ncrack 10.0.0.130:21 192.168.1.2:22

Starting Ncrack 0.01ALPHA ( http://ncrack.org ) at 2009-07-24 23:05 EEST

Discovered credentials for ftp on 10.0.0.130 21/tcp:
10.0.0.130 21/tcp ftp: admin hello1
Discovered credentials for ssh on 192.168.1.2 22/tcp:
192.168.1.2 22/tcp ssh: guest 12345
192.168.1.2 22/tcp ssh: admin money$

Ncrack done: 2 services scanned in 156.03 seconds.

Ncrack finished.

    </screen>
    </example>

  </refsect1>

  <para>
    The latest version of Ncrack can be obtained from
    <ulink url="http://ncrack.org" />. The latest version of this man page is
    available at http://ncrack.org/man.html .
  </para>
  
  <refsect1 id='man-briefoptions'>
    <title>Options Summary</title>

    <para>
      This options summary is printed when Ncrack is run with no arguments.
      It helps people remember the most common options, but is no substitute
      for the in-depth documentation in the rest of this manual.
    </para>
     <indexterm class="startofrange" id="ncrack-usage-indexterm">
       <primary sortas="#">summary of options</primary>
     </indexterm>
     <indexterm class="startofrange" id="ncrack-usage-ncrack-indexterm">
       <primary>command-line options</primary>
       <secondary>of Ncrack</secondary>
     </indexterm>
      &ncrack-usage;
      <indexterm class="endofrange" startref="ncrack-usage-ncrack-indexterm"/>
      <indexterm class="endofrange" startref="ncrack-usage-indexterm"/>
   </refsect1>


  <refsect1 id="man-target-specification">
    <title>Target Specification</title>
    <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>target specification</primary>
    </indexterm>

     <para>
       Everything on the Ncrack command-line that isn't an option (or an
       option argument) is treated as a target host specification. The
       simplest case is to specify a target IP address or a hostname.
     </para>

     <para>
       Sometimes you wish to crack a whole network of adjacent hosts.
       For this, Ncrack supports CIDR-style <indexterm significance="normal">
       <primary>CIDR (Classless Inter-Domain Routing)</primary></indexterm>
       addressing. You can append /<replaceable>numbits</replaceable> to an
       IPv4 address or hostname and Ncrack will try to crack every IP
       address for which the first numbits are the same as for the
       reference IP or hostname given. For example, 192.168.10.0/24 would
       send probes to the 256 hosts between 192.168.10.0
       <literal moreinfo="none">11000000 10101000 00001010 00000000</literal>)
       and 192.168.10.255 (binary:
       <literal moreinfo="none">11000000 10101000 00001010 11111111</literal>),
       inclusive. 192.168.10.40/24 would crack exactly the same targets.
       Given that the host <literal moreinfo="none">scanme.nmap.org</literal>
       <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>
       <literal moreinfo="none">scanme.nmap.org</literal></primary></indexterm>
       is at the IP address 64.13.134.52, the specification
       scanme.nmap.org/16 would send probes to the 65,536 IP addresses
       between 64.13.0.0 and 64.13.255.255. The smallest allowed value is
       /0, which targets the whole Internet. The largest value is /32,
       which targets just the named host or IP address because all address
       bits are fixed.
      </para>
 
      <indexterm significance="normal"><primary>address ranges</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        CIDR notation is short but not always flexible enough.  For example,
        you might want to send probes to 192.168.0.0/16 but skip any IPs
        ending with .0 or .255 because they may be used as subnet network
        and broadcast addresses. Ncrack supports this through octet range
        addressing. Rather than specify a normal IP address, you can specify
        a comma-separated list of numbers or ranges for each octet. For
        example, 192.168.0-255.1-254 will skip all addresses in the range
        that end in .0 or .255, and 192.168.3-5,7.1 will target the four
        addresses 192.168.3.1, 192.168.4.1, 192.168.5.1, and 192.168.7.1.
        Either side of a range may be omitted; the default values are 0 on
        the left and 255 on the right. Using
        <literal moreinfo="none">-</literal> by itself is the same as 0-255,
        but remember to use 0- in the first octet so the target
        specification doesn't look like a command-line option. Ranges need
        not be limited to the final octets: the specifier will send probes
        to all IP addresses on the Internet ending in 13.37 This sort of
        broad sampling can be useful for Internet surveys and research.
      </para>
 
      <para>
        Ncrack accepts multiple host specifications on the command line,
        and they don't need to be the same type. The command
        <command moreinfo="none">ncrack scanme.nmap.org
        192.168.0.0/8 10.0.0,1,3-7.- -p22</command> does what you would expect.
      </para>
 
      <para>
        While targets are usually specified on the command lines, the
        following options are also available to control target selection:
      </para>


  </refsect1>


  <refsect1 id='man-bugs'>
   <title>Bugs</title>
   <indexterm><primary>bugs, reporting</primary></indexterm>

  <para>
    Like its authors, Ncrack isn't perfect. But you can help make
    it better by sending bug reports or even writing patches. If Ncrack
    doesn't behave the way you expect, first upgrade to the latest
    version available from <ulink url="http://ncrack.org"/>. If the
    problem persists, do some research to determine whether it has already
    been discovered and addressed. Try searching for the error message on our
    search page at <ulink url="http://insecure.org/search.html"/> or at
    Google. Also try browsing the <citetitle>nmap-dev</citetitle> archives
    at <ulink url="http://seclists.org/"/> .
    <indexterm><primary> <citetitle>nmap-dev</citetitle> mailing list
    </primary></indexterm>
    Read this full manual page as well. If nothing comes of this, mail a bug
    report to <email>nmap-dev@insecure.org</email> . Please include
    everything you have learned about the problem, as well as what version of
    Nmap you are running and what operating system version it is running on.
    Problem reports and Ncrack usage questions sent to
    <email>nmap-dev@insecure.org</email> are far more likely to be answered
    than those sent to Fyodor directly. If you subscribe to the nmap-dev
    list before posting, your message will bypass moderation and get through
    more quickly. Subscribe at 
    <ulink url="http://cgi.insecure.org/mailman/listinfo/nmap-dev"/> .
  </para>

  <para>
    Code patches to fix bugs are even better than bug reports.
    Basic instructions for creating patch files with your changes are
    available at <ulink url="http://nmap.org/data/HACKING" /> . Patches may
    be sent to <citetitle>nmap-dev</citetitle> (recommended) or to Fyodor
    directly.
  </para>

  </refsect1>


  <refsect1 id="man-author">
    <title>Authors</title>
    <para>ithilgore <email>ithilgore.ryu.l@gmail.com</email>
      (<ulink url="http://sock-raw.org" />)</para>
    <para>Fyodor <email>fyodor@insecure.org</email>
      (<ulink url="http://insecure.org" />)</para>
  </refsect1>


</refentry>

<indexterm class="endofrange" startref="man-ncrack-indexterm"
  significance="normal"/>
